## Dr. KRISHNA KANT CHINTALAPUDI

Principal Researcher, Microsoft Research Labs Redmond,

Website: https://chintalapudikkc.github.io/ Email: chintalapudi.krishna@gmail.com

**Goal.** Leadership position to incubate and develop products and drive business in a large addressable market with a high technical barrier.

**Summary.** I have 18+ years of research and development experience in inventing novel and disruptive ideas and delivering them as products and platform solutions. I have research and technical expertise is AI/ML, Video Analytics, Networking & Systems and Internet of Things.

- **Xbox** (2021-current) Led the research and development to deliver the communication protocols for Next Generation Xbox Console and Controllers, a 3.8B USD revenue market with a 9% CAGR, to achieve state of the art latency and power consumption. Led two teams, one with 2 researchers and the other with 20 developers over a period of three years. Worked with other teams in Xbox through various stages of the product lifecycle including Business Opportunity Proposal, Product Definition, RFP and Vendor Selection, Architecture Specification and Product Development.
- Incubation, City Scale IoT (2017-2020) Pitched a business opportunity proposal targeting a 10B USD total addressable market to Satya Nadella to leverage cutting edge research in IoT technology. The technology would incur 30-100X reduction in CAPEX and OPEX for city scale IoT with higher reliability. Subsequently, I led an incubation effort with the Compass Group as our customer to deliver a solution for field services covering 300sq m including Redmond, Sammamish, Bothell, Medina, Bellevue and parts of Seattle) for field services such as food, water and beverage delivery. During this time, I led a research team as well as worked with other Microsoft teams, external vendors and partners across the project lifecycle. This idea was selected among the top five projects in the annual Microsoft Disruptive Technology Review.
- Azure ML (2016-2019) Pioneered the research and development for the first large scale automated crowdsourcing based
  groundtruth annotation service, "Satyam" to enable training and maintenance of machine vision models for video analytics,
  including object classification, detection, segmentation and video tracking. Subsequently, worked with Azure ML to
  incorporate Satyam's multi-annotation fusion and quality control into the Azure machine learning labelling service within
  the Azure Machine Learning Platform.
- **Video Analytics Solution (2016)-** Delivered and deployed a solution for real time per lane car counting for the city of Bellevue as a part of the city's Vision Zero Initiative.
- Indoor Location Service (2011-2015) Pioneered the first technique for large scale indoor localization by leveraging crowdsourcing on mobile phones EZ and Zee (2500+ research citations). It used Al-based techniques to learn the radio propagation models in the indoor environment from measurements crowdsourced from multiple users. Subsequently, worked with product teams to deliver the Orion Indoor localization service that was deployed in over 50 malls and airports.
- Hard Real Time Industrial Control (2006-2009) Designed, implemented and tested a wireless research protype communication device to deliver a reliability of 10^-9 and latency bounds of 20ms for industrial control systems in Bosch.
- **Thought Leadership** Fundamental research with 40+ peer reviewed research publications in flagship conferences with 8500+ citations and awarded 30+ USPTO patents.
- Academia Impact mentored and managed researchers who are now faculty at universities such as UIUC, Cornell, NYU, Georgia Tech, UC Irvine. Part of Conference PC for conferences such as SIGCOMM, Mobicom. Mobisys.
- Academic Partnerships managed research partnerships with universities such as MIT, CMU, University of Washington, University of Wisconsin Madison, Rice University etc. and co-mentored students and junior faculty.

### **Work Experience**

• Principal Researcher, Microsoft Research, Redmond, Networking Research Group

(Dec 2015-current)

• Researcher, Microsoft Research, India, Bangalore, Networking and Systems

(Apr 2009- Dec 2015)

• Bosch Research and Technology Centre, Palo Alto, CA, USA

(Sept 2005-Apr 2009)

# Education

- PhD in Computer Science, University of Southern California, Los Angeles, CA 2006.
- MS in Electrical Engineering, Networking, University of Southern California, Los Angles, CA 2002.
- MS in Electrical Engineering, Signal Processing and Control Systems, Drexel University, Philadelphia, PA 1999.
- BTech in Electrical Engineering, Indian Institute of Technology (IIT) Varanasi, India 1997.

### **Recent Awards and News Coverage**

- Accurate Media Time-Synchronization for Cloud Gaming (2023) Recent work on time-synchronization for cloud gaming published in SIGCOMM 2023, received wide news coverage including MIT news, Tech Times, Science Daily etc.
- o **ACM Test of Time Award (2022)** Awarded the ACM Test of Time Award for my pioneering work on structural health monitoring. The award is given to research that has had a significant impact on the field for over a decade.

#### **Select Publications**

- **SIGCOMM 2023** "Ekho: Synchronizing Cloud Gaming Media Across Multiple Endpoints", Pouya Hamadanian, Doug Gallatin, Mohammad Alizadeh, Krishna Chintalapudi, (**Networking, Cloud Gaming, AR/VR**)
- ICLR 2023 "MCAL: Minimum Cost Human Labelling", Hang Qiu, Krishna Chintalapudi, Ramesh Govindan, ICLR 2023 (AI/ML)
- NSDI 2023 "OpenLoRa: Validating LoRa Implementations through an Extensible and Open-sourced Framework", Manan Mishra, Daniel Koch, Muhammad Osama Shahid, Bhuvana Krishnaswamy, Krishna Chintalapudi, Suman Banerjee, NSDI 2023 (Networking, IoT)
- ASPLOS 2023 "Kodan: Addressing the Computational Bottleneck in Space", Brad Denby, Brandon Lucia, Shadi Noghabi, Krishna Chintalapudi, Ranveer Chandra, *ASPLOS 2023* (AI, Compute in Space, Networking)
- Mobicom 2022 BSMA: scalable LoRa networks using full duplex gateways Raghav Subbaraman, Yeswanth Guntupalli,, Shruti Jain, Rohit Kumar, Krishna Chintalapudi, Dinesh Bharadia MobiCom '22: Proceedings of the 28th Annual International Conference on Mobile Computing And Networking October 2022 (IoT)
- Hotnets 2021 "Towards a Cost vs. Quality Sweet Spot for Monitoring Networks", Nofel Yaseen, Behnaz Arzani, Krishna Chintalapudi, Vaishnavi Ranganathan, Felipe Vieira Frujeri, Kevin Hsieh, Daniel S. Berger, Vincent Liu, Srikanth Kandula, HotNets 2021, (Networking, Telemetry)
- **SIGCOMM 2021** "Concurrent Interference Cancellation: Decoding Multi-Packet Collisions in LoRa", Muhammad Osama Shahid, Millan Philipose, Krishna Chintalapudi, Suman Banerjee, Bhuvana Krishnaswamy, *ACM SIGCOMM 2021*, (**Networking, IoT**)
- **SIGSPATIAL 2020** "Optimizing Onsite Food Services at Scale", Konstantina Mellou, Luke Marshall, Krishna Chintalapudi, Patrick Jaillet, Ishai Menache, *ACM SIGSPATIAL 2020* (IoT, Optimization)
- **Mobicom 2019** "Blind Distributed MU-MIMO for IoT Networking over VHF Narrowband Spectrum", Chuhan Gao, Mehrdad Hessar, Krishna Chintalapudi, Bodhi Priyantha, *MobiCom 2019* (IoT, Networking)
- HotMobile 2018 Creating the Perfect Illusion: What will it take to Create Life-Like Virtual Reality Headsets? Eduardo Cuervo,
   Krishna Chintalapudi, Manikanta Kotaru, HotMobile'18 February 2018 (AR/VR)
- arXiv 2018 "SATYAM: Democratizing Groundtruth for Machine Vision", Krishna Chintalapudi, Hang Qiu, Ramesh Govindan, (arXiv 2018) (Al, Machine Vision, Video Analytics)
- IEEE Computer 2017 "Real-time Video Analytics: the killer app for edge computing", Ganesh Ananthanarayanan, Victor Bahl, Peter Bodík, Krishna Chintalapudi, Matthai Philipose, Lenin Ravindranath Sivalingam, Sudipta Sinha, IEEE Computer, 2017 (AI/ML, Video Analytics)
- Mobicom 2014 Enabling Physical Analytics in Retail Stores Using Smart Glasses Swati Rallapalli, Aishwarya Ganesan, Krishna Chintalapudi, Venkat Padmanabhan, Lili Qiu, ACM Mobicom 2014 September 2014 (AI, Video Analytics)
- **SIGCOMM 2013-** Dhwani: Secure Peer-to-Peer Acoustic NFC, Krishna Chintalapudi, Venkat Padmanabhan, Ramarathnam Venkatesan, SIGCOMM August 2013 (**Wireless Communication**)
- Mobicom 2012 Centaur : Locating Devices in an Office Environment, Krishna Chintalapudi, Venkat Padmanabhan, Mobicom August 2012 (AI/ML, IoT)
- Mobicom 2012 Zee: Zero-Effort Crowdsourcing for Indoor Localization, Krishna Kant Chintalapudi, Venkat Padmanabhan, Rijurekha Sen, Mobicom August 2012 (AI/ML, IoT)
- NSDI 2012 WiFi-NC: WiFi Over Narrow Channels, Krishna Chintalapudi, Bozidar Radunovic, Vlad Balan, Michael Buettener, Vishnu Navda, Ramachandran Ramjee, Srinivas Yerramalli, NSDI April 2012 (Wireless Communication, Networking)
- **Mobicom 2010** Indoor Localization Without the Pain Krishna Chintalapudi, Anand Padmanabha Iyer, Venkat Padmanabhan, Mobicom September 2010 (AI/ML, IoT)
- IEEE SMC'98 Krishna Kant Chintalapudi and Moshe Kam, "The Credibilistic Fuzzy C Means Algorithm", Proc. IEEE SMC'98, pp.(2034-2040). (AI/ML)
- IEEE SMC 1998 K.K.Chintalapudi and N.R.Pal, "A Novel Scheme to Reduce and Determine the Architecture of a Multilayer Perceptron Network," Proc. of the IEEE Conference on Systems, Man, and Cybernetics, pp. 2034-2040, 1998 (AI/ML)
- INPSC 1997 N.R Pal and K.K Chintalapudi, "Feature selection in a connectionist framework", International journal of Neural, Parallel and Scientific Computation. Vol.5, pp. (359-382), 1997. (AI/ML)